<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>UPLB Eliens - Tutorials and Guides</title><link href="https://uplb-eliens.github.io/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="https://uplb-eliens.github.io/feeds/tutorials-and-guides.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>https://uplb-eliens.github.io/</id><updated>2022-08-29T00:00:00+08:00</updated><subtitle>Competitive Programming Team</subtitle><entry><title>What is Competitive Programming?</title><link href="https://uplb-eliens.github.io/what-is-competitive-programming.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2022-08-29T00:00:00+08:00</published><updated>2022-08-28T00:00:00+08:00</updated><author><name>katipuzer0</name></author><id>tag:uplb-eliens.github.io,2022-08-29:/what-is-competitive-programming.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Introduction&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In Competitive Programming, competitors are given a set of programming problems to solve within a given time period. The competitor who solved the most problems or has accumulated the highest score is declared the winner. Competitors need to train and practice to win, just like in sports or games …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Introduction&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In Competitive Programming, competitors are given a set of programming problems to solve within a given time period. The competitor who solved the most problems or has accumulated the highest score is declared the winner. Competitors need to train and practice to win, just like in sports or games. The types of programming problems usually involve data structures and algorithms as well as math concepts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;How to start?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First, learn the basics of programming and the features of the programming language you want to use. After taking CMSC 12, CMSC 21, and CMSC 22, you should understand variables, data types, recursion, operators, I/O facilities, control flow, arrays, and strings, searching, sorting, etc. of Python3, C, and Java. You should be able to translate basic algorithms into working and correct code.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Second, learn some Discrete Mathematics. You can get this from CMSC 56 and CMSC 57. These courses do not require coding and mostly use pen and paper. However, I recommend you attempt to implement the algorithms studied in these courses. Understand set theory, counting techniques, methods of proofs, trees, graphs, and some automata.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Third, learn some Data Structures and Algorithm Analysis. You can get this from CMSC 123. Master linked lists, stacks, queues, hash tables, trees, graphs, etc. You will also be introduced to algorithm analysis to determine the performance of algorithms. Knowing this is important because some problems will require solutions that have bounds in terms of time and memory. Using more efficient (in terms of time and storage) data structures and algorithms might be needed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lastly, practice solving problems on online platforms. I recommend &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://open.kattis.com/universities/uplb.edu.ph"&gt;Kattis&lt;/a&gt; for beginners. Try to stay on the #1 spot. Most problem statements have some &amp;quot;story.&amp;quot; &lt;em&gt;An excellent skill to develop is how to extract the &amp;quot;core&amp;quot; problem hidden in the story&lt;/em&gt;. Always solve first with pen and paper before writing code. Also, make sure to consider &amp;quot;edge cases&amp;quot; in your solutions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lab exercises in the courses mentioned above are relatively easy compared to the problems in competitive programming. You might be overwhelmed while starting, but don't give up.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Code Quality&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sadly, code for competitive programming does not need to be readable and maintainable in the traditional sense of software engineering. Your program reads an input file(or from stdin) and then writes to an output file(or to stdout). The code with the minimum lines of code that solves a problem correctly is ideal. Forget using human-readable variable names. Use the C preprocessor to create shorthands for loops etc. Sometimes you don't need to implement data structures from scratch. Use the built-in libraries in the language, such as STL in C++. I highly recommend learning C++ for competitive programming.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;What's in it for you?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It can improve your problem-solving and programming skills, which &lt;em&gt;might&lt;/em&gt; be helpful in technical interviews when applying for a job. For a competitive person like me who love CS, it's just for fun.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Final Notes&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After completing CMSC 123 and practicing regularly (1 to 2 hours a day), you can make progress on your own. Study more advanced topics and solve more complex problems. Test your skills in actual competitions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For more information, check this &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://github.com/uplb-eliens/awesome-competitive-programming"&gt;repo&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</content><category term="Tutorials and Guides"></category></entry></feed>